בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is ל"ה, Lamed Hey, and
but we we pick up ל"ד עמוד ב' Lamed Daled amud bet
about a a quarter of the way down, the two dots, דם
טהורה שמצורעת. dam tehorah shemetzora'at. So here is a case where to
remind everybody that we say that the מעיינות, ma'ayanot, the spit and
the urine of a זב zav and a זבה zavah and of
a נידה niddah are an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, are a primary
source of טומאה, tumah, and the question and urine, okay? And other
so the question is like what other liquids are included in that?
So the question is, so the basic definition the גמרא Gemara has
is מתעגל ויוצא, mit'agel veyotzei, has to be things that are like
collected in the body and then come out, so you see how
that's true by spit and urine. So
what about the so anyway, so the question is about what do
you say about about menstrual blood? Now normally it's a moot question
because menstrual blood is itself the source of being a נידה niddah
or זבה, zavah, so it's an אב הטומאה av hatumah by virtue
of it being the you know the basis of the טומאה. tumah.
But there are cases where that's not true. So for example, if
the woman is during her during the after childbirth, after one week
or two weeks of childbirth, where the blood is considered טהורה, tehorah,
then what is the status? Now if she actually has gone to
the מקווה mikvah after that and she's a יולדת, yoledet, it's also
a moot point because she's טהורה, tehorah, so who cares about her
fluids? But the scenario in the משנה Mishnah is is that she
is a מצורעת, metzora'at, she has leprosy, where the same הלכה halacha
true about the fluids of of somebody with צרעת. tzara'at. So a
woman who has צרעת tzara'at who her fluids are אב הטומאה, av
hatumah, what is the source of her menstrual blood after the week
or two of childbirth? That is the question. Okay? So is that
considered to be like the spit and the and the urine?
So here exactly the fluids have yes,
that is that is correct. So here בית שמאי Beit Shammai says
it is it is טהור, tahor, and בית הלל Beit Hillel says
that it is טמא, tamei, it does have the status of the
fluids like the spit and the urine. So let's take a look
at the גמרא Gemara about a quarter of the way down on
ל"ד עמוד
ב'.
Lamed
Daled amud bet. Yes, but some fluids are considered just as טמא
tamei as you yourself are.
So what's the concept? Is the concept that you are your fluids
or that your fluids are something different than?
I don't know.
You know, it's hard to know by these טומאה, tumah, what exactly
maybe is there some concept of these being vital fluids, but that
wouldn't be true because if anything of that were true would be
more about the blood than about things like spit and urine.
You know,
I don't have a good construct here. Okay, so let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמא דבית הלל? Mai ta'ama deBeit
Hillel? What's the reason of בית הלל Beit Hillel that they consider
this to be a like a spit and urine? We're about a
quarter of the way down on ל"ד עמוד ב', Lamed Daled amud
bet, דם טהורה שמצורעת. dam tehorah shemetzora'at. אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi
Yitzchak, לזכר. lazachar. It says that that at the end of that
the פרשה parsha says this is the you know, this is the
טומאה tumah
what's the פסוק? pasuk? הזב וזובו לזכר ולנקבה ולאיש אשר תצא ממנו
שכבת זרע. Hazav vezovo lazachar velanekevah ule'ish asher tetzei mimenu shichvat zara.
So at the end of the פרשה parsha of זב zav and
זבה zavah it says these this is the טומאה tumah for the
male and the female. So what's that extra why do we need
that extra פסוק pasuk male and female? I mean we've been talking
about that until now. So לזכר לרבות מצורע למעיינותיו, lazachar lerabot metzora
lema'ayanotav,
not only include the male זב, zav, but a different type of
a male, the male מצורע metzora that his wellsprings are טמא, tamei,
ולנקבה לרבות מצורעת למעיינותיה velanekevah lerabot metzora'at lema'ayanoteha wellsprings here being these
types of things like spit and urine. ולנקבה לרבות מצורעת למעיינותיה, velanekevah
lerabot metzora'at lema'ayanoteha,
a female מצורעת metzora'at for her wellsprings, meaning the תורה Torah is
explicit about the spit of a זב zav and a זבה, zavah,
but it is not explicit about a מצורע metzora and a מצורעת,
metzora'at, so these extra words male and female come to include even
somebody with צרעת. tzara'at. So now, okay fine, that's הלכה, halacha, but
how does that get you still to the blood? So here's the
דרשה. drasha. מה מעיינותיה, ma ma'ayanoteha, what are what sort of wellsprings
fluids of this female מצורעת? metzora'at? אילימא שאר מעיינותיה, ileima she'ar ma'ayanoteha,
if it's the normal types of things, spit and urine, מזכר נפקא,
mizachar nafka, why would you have to tell me? Once you told
me by a male with צרעת, tzara'at, of course it's true by
a female. I mean, you know, the תורה Torah why should it
distinguish between a male and a female? So I would have known
spit and urine. So therefore אלא לדמה, ela ledamah,
if it's mentioning female in particular, it means that there's a particular
fluid which is only by a female, and that is her blood.
So the blood of a female menstrual blood here I mean I
should say more uterine blood, that is טמא tamei as a fluid
even if it's not טמא tamei as blood itself. So it's from
the דרשה drasha of ולנקבה. velanekevah. לטמא דם טהורה שלה, letammei dam
tehorah shelah,
to say that even the blood of hers that is not טמא
tamei because of נידה niddah blood is טמא tamei as a fluid
of a מצורעת. metzora'at. ובית שמאי, uveit Shammai, what does בית שמאי
Beit Shammai say? לנקבה מזכר לא
אתיא, lanekevah mizachar lo atya, no it had to say נקבה nekevah
separate from male, there's no special inclusion of the blood, but it
you can't learn one from the other. Why can't you learn female
from male about the fluids of a מצורע? metzora? דאיכא למפרך מה
לזכר שכן טעון פריעה ופרימה. de'ika lemifrach mah lazachar sheken ta'un pri'ah
ufreimah.
the status of a male מצורע metzora is more weighty than that
of a female. A male מצורע metzora at least his practice is,
he has to let his hair grow wild, he has to rent
his clothes, he cannot have sex. None of these things are true
by a female מצורע, metzora, correct? מתוך לו וחוץ לו לא ולא
מחוץ לו אלא mi-toch lo ve-chutz lo lo ve-la mi-chutz lo ela
we have a דרשה. drasha.
So therefore because the practices of a male מצורע metzora are more
strict, I might have thought that just because his fluids are טמא
tamei is not true about a female. תאמר Tomar
by a female where these practices are not true, maybe her fluids
would not be טמא, tamei, so it has to say female. And
therefore you cannot learn a special new type of a fluid for
a female. ובית הלל, U'Beit Hillel, what does בית הלל Beit Hillel
say back? לכתוב רחמנא בנקבה ולא בעי זכר. Lichtov rachmana benekeiva velo
ba'ei zachar. No. Okay, I admit to you that female you can't
infer because it's less weighty, but say it the other way. Say
by a female that her fluids are טמא tamei and don't bother
saying it by a male. דאנן אמרינן, De-anan amrinan, I would have
said ומה נקבה שאינה טעונה פריעה ופרימה ואינה אסורה בתשמיש המיטה, u'ma
nekeiva she-eina teuna priah u-frimah ve-eina asura be-tashmish ha-mitah, what's the case
by a female that doesn't have to let her hair grow wild
or rent her clothes or is forbidden in sex, a female who
is a מצורעה metzora'ah who has צרעת, tzaraat, and even though her
practices are less severe, nevertheless רבתה רחמנא מעיינותיה, rabta rachmana mayanoteha,
the Torah still says that her fluids are טמא, tamei, so זכר
לא כל שכן, zachar lo kol she-ken, isn't it more so by
a male that since his practices are more severe, certainly his fluids
should be טמא? tamei? So therefore it is redundant to say, right,
you didn't have to say it by female, but you didn't have
to say it by male, I could have inferred. So אם אינו
עניין לזכר, im eino inyan le-zachar, if you don't need to tell
me by a male מצורע metzora that his fluids are טמא, tamei,
תנהו עניין לנקבה, tnehu inyan le-nekeiva, so it's an extra, it's an
extra word and therefore it's coming to tell me, it has nothing
to tell me about male, let it tell me something about female.
Ah yes you can, ואם אינו עניין למעיינותיה ve-im eino inyan le-mayanoteha
and if it's not needed for her normal fluids because that's explicit,
תנהו עניין לדם, tnehu inyan le-dam, tell about a new type of
a fluid, her blood. Now again the reason that blood needs a
special category is as I said, blood is not מתעגל ויוצא, mit'agel
ve-yotzei, it doesn't fall in the normal category of מעיינות, mayanot, of
the fluids which are things that collect and then come out like
urine and sweat. And therefore according to בית הלל Beit Hillel it
says you're right, it's not standardly in that category, but the extra
פסוק pasuk tells us that that as if it were in that
category that's also included. And בית שמאי Beit Shammai does not believe
in that extra פסוק. pasuk. Okay, ובית שמאי, u-Beit Shammai, what would
בית שמאי Beit Shammai say? דתני דם טהור שלה de-tani dam tahor
she-la that even the טהור tahor blood is treated as a fluid.
ובית שמאי, u-Beit Shammai, what would בית שמאי Beit Shammai say back?
זכר מנקבה לא אתי. zachar mi-nekeiva lo atei. No, I you can't
you couldn't have just said it by female and learned male from
that, why? דאיכא למיפרך, de-ika le-mifrach, you could have challenged it. מה
לנקבה שכן מטמאה באונס? ma le-nekeiva she-ken metameia be-ones? או באונס, be-ones,
תאמר בזכר דלא. tomar be-zachar de-lo.
That by a at least by מצורע metzora you're right, a female
is more lenient, but nevertheless there's ways in which a female has
is weightier by laws of טומאה. tumah. What is that? When it
comes to זב וזבה. zav ve-zava. A female
who has who bleeds whether it's because of natural things or external
stimulation or something you know whether even באונס, be-ones, even by something
external that caused the bleeding, she could still be a נידה niddah
or a זבה. zava. By a man who has a flow as
a זב, zav, some penile flow that's non-semen, that's not when it's
caused by some external cause. So the so a female is weightier
that even when her status of a זבה zava is caused externally,
תאמר בזכר דלא tomar be-zachar de-lo and by a male that's not
true. So therefore if you said fluids by a female you couldn't
have learned it by a male because there's ways in which the
female category is more weighty. Now of course that's not so great
because as בית הלל Beit Hillel will say back, ובית הלל, u'Beit
Hillel, טומאה במצורע פרכינן מילי דזב? tumah be-metzora parchinnan milei de-zav?
We're talking about a מצורע. metzora. We're trying to discuss how do
you know the laws of a fluids of a מצורע. metzora. And
I'm saying say it by female and I can say if it's
true by a female that has lighter laws of טומאה tumah certainly
by male. So how can you say oh no no female's more
weightier when it comes to זב. zav. Who cares about זב? zav?
We're not talking about זב, zav, we're talking about מצורע. metzora. All
right. ובית שמאי, u-Beit Shammai, שום טומאה פרכינן. shum tumah parchinnan. Yeah
it doesn't matter, once in the world of טומאה tumah it's weightier
you cannot say it by one and learn it out by the
other. Okay so that's basically the דרשה drasha of בית הלל Beit
Hillel which is that the there's an extra word male and female
to tell you that even the special fluids of a female, uterine
blood which a male doesn't have, have this law of fluids. אי
בעית אימא Ei bayit eima if you want, אמרי לך ובית שמאי,
amri lach u-Beit Shammai, בית שמאי Beit Shammai will say to you,
האי לזכר, hai le-zachar,
here's why you needed to say לזכר. le-zachar. You're right, you could
have said it by female and learned out male about fluids. So
why does it say male? מיבעי ליה לזכר כל שהוא זכר, Mibayei
le-zachar kol she-hu zachar,
anybody who is a male, בין גדול בין קטן, bein gadol bein
katan, whether an adult or a minor. You remember we learned before
the whole question about how do you know that a female or
a male that has that has bleeding, uterine bleeding even from the
moment she's born or a male that has penile flow even from
the day one day old can be a זב zav or a
זבה, zava, and we learned it out from לזכר, le-zachar, male, it
doesn't say man it doesn't say woman it says male, even a
one day old can have these טומאות. tumot. So that's what you
learn it out from, you learned to teach me that and not
to teach me this idea of these new a new fluid. ובית
הלל, u'Beit Hillel, בית הלל Beit Hillel נפקא להו מזאת תורת הזב.
nafka lehu mi-zot torat ha-zav. This is the law of the זב.
zav. So זאת תורת, zot torat, this is the law of, is
always seen as a big inclusive statement. So that tells you בין
גדול בין קטן, bein gadol bein katan, whether male or female, excuse
me, whether adult or minor it all applies. Alright, at the end
of the day, it's a question of how to use this word,
how to use that word, but the basic point that בית הלל
beis hillel says is, we have an extra word לזכר ולנקבה l'zachar
u'l'nekeivah to tell me that even though the uterine blood is not
מתעגל ויוצא, mitageil v'yotzei, so it's not collected and come out, although
it's a little ironic because uterine blood does מתעגל ויוצא mitageil v'yotzei
and as that מתעגל, mitageil, it sort of lines the uterus and
it forms a lining and then it comes out. It's not sort
of like urine and spit which collect as a fluid, but nevertheless,
the גמרא gemara understands that it's not classically in that category. According
to בית הלל beis hillel you have an extra פסוק pasuk to
tell me that it has that status. Now as I said, normally
this is moot, because normally if a person whose fluids are טמא
tamei come out, then those fluids are טמא tamei not as her
fluids, but because it's the source of טומאה. tumah. Even a woman
who is טמאה tmei'ah for blood, uterine blood comes out, that's טמא
tamei not as her fluids, but because it's the source of טומאה.
tumah. It either makes her a נדה niddah or a זבה. zavah.
So it's a whole moot question. So the way it's not moot
is when that blood does not make her a נדה niddah and
זבה. zavah. When is that? During the sixty-six or thirty-three days after
childbirth. Now, okay, but then it's moot because she's not טמאה. tmei'ah.
Oh no, she's טמאה tmei'ah from a different standpoint. She's a מצורע.
metzora. So it's very ingenious how they try to get exactly the
case which allows us to test the question of what is the
status of uterine blood, is it considered the fluids of a זב
zav and a מצורע? metzora? And that is debated by בית הלל
beis hillel and בית שמאי. beis shammai. Now the גמרא gemara shifts
gears a little bit in a way that I
think is a little bit more conceptually interesting. Let's take a look.
The גמרא gemara says like this: אמר רב יוסף, amar rav yosef,
so the second wide line of ל"ד עמוד ב', lamed daled amud
beis, says רב יוסף, rav yosef, כי פשי ריש לקיש בזב, ki
pashi reish lakish b'zav, when ריש לקיש reish lakish is learning or
דרשנ-ing darshan-ing laws of a זב, zav, בעי הכי, ba'ei hachi, he
always raises this question: ראיה ראשונה של זב קטן מהו שתטמא במגע.
re'iah rishonah shel zav katan mahu shet'tamei b'maga. Now the הלכה halacha
is the following: again, we'll say it explicitly at the עמוד ב'
amud beis of ל"ה, lamed hey, that there's a physical difference. By
a woman, the difference between נדה niddah and זב, zav, it's both
uterine blood, the difference is what time of the month is it
coming out, during her period or not during her period of time,
determined by certain ways we've discussed before. By a man, it has
nothing to do with timing, it has to do with what is
the fluid. If it is semen, then he is a בעל קרי,
ba'al keri, then it's seminal emission, he is טמא tamei for one
day, end of story. If it is non-semen and it is something
not like blood or whatever, we'll see, it's basically a type of
a loose clear liquid, not as viscous as semen and clearer
than semen, then that makes him a זב. zav. And then if
it happens once, he's a one-day טומאה, tumah, twice he's seven days,
and three times he brings a קרבן. korban. That's the law of
a זב. zav. By the way, you have some people try to
say that this is maybe some type of venereal disease, cause I
don't know, do venereal diseases lead to these type of penile emissions?
Do they look like this? Does anybody know? No? Doctors in the
room?
No? Okay. Anyway. Well, you did go to medical school for a
while a few years ago. Alright, anyway.
Anyway, anyway, but now the interesting הלכה halacha is like this. The
first time he has this flow, although it's a זיבה ziva flow
and not שכבת זרע, shichvat zera, not semen, his halachic status is
like שכבת זרע. shichvat zera. His halachic status is a one-day טומאה,
tumah, he goes to the מקוה. mikvah. Okay, so it has the
same halachic status as a בעל קרי. ba'al keri. Now here's the
question. Here's
ריש לקיש's reish lakish's question. So this first flow he has, okay,
which is not semen, if he is a minor, זב קטן, zav
katan, is he טמא? tamei? Why is that a question? Because all
these טומאות, tumos, זב, zav, זבה, zavah, and נדה, niddah, as we
just learned from פסוקים, psukim, זכר, zachar, נקבה nekeivah and other פסוקים,
psukim, begin even one day old. The one טומאה tumah of these
bodily fluids that do not begin one day old is בעל קרי,
ba'al keri, is seminal emission. There because that's associated with sex, and
we learn from a פסוק, pasuk, you know we learn from other
things or whatever, tradition, that an act of sex is only defined
as nine years old and a day for a boy. So therefore
the seminal emission of a boy under nine years old and a
day is not considered שכבת זרע, shichvat zera, he's not טמא. tamei.
Okay, so now the question is, let's say he has this זיבה
ziva flow. Okay, you understand sort of the cross-categorizing here? As a
זב zav he'll become טמא tamei if it's two or three times.
But if it's one time, his טומאה tumah is equivalent to that
of semen, of a בעל קרי, ba'al keri, and it's learned from
the פסוק pasuk of that. So is he טמא tamei after only
one time, because he cannot become טמא tamei as a בעל קרי?
ba'al keri? That's the question. Okay. ראיה ראשונה של זב
קטן מהו שתטמא במגע,
re'iah rishonah shel zav
katan mahu shet'tamei b'maga, if he's a minor,
is he now טמא tamei with through touch, or maybe is the
semen itself מטמא? metamei? זאת תורת הזב אשר תצא ממנו שכבת זרע.
zot torat hazav asher taitzei mimenu shichvat zera.
This is where we learn out that the first time it's like
he had a seminal emission, this is the law of the זב
zav and the man from whom comes out a semen, אמר רחמנא,
amar rachmana, כל ששכבת זרע שלו מטמא ראיה ראשונה שלו מטמא. kol
sheshichvat zera shelo m'tamei re'iah rishonah shelo m'tamei.
Any person who's in a category where his semen would be טמא,
tamei, meaning he's over nine years old, similarly
his זיבה Ziva flow is also טמא tamei because it has the
same status of טומאה tumah as if it were for the first
time, as if it was שכבת זרע, shichvat zera, שכבת זרע, shichvat
zera, ראייה ראשונה שלו
מטמא. re'iyah rishona shelo metamai. והאי, Ve'hai, and this minor, כיוון דשכבת
זרעו לא מטמא, keivan de'shichvat zaro lo metamai, since his semen does
not cause טומאה, tumah, ראייה ראשונה נמי לא תטמא, re'iyah rishona nami
lo titma, so the same is true about his זיבה Ziva flow.
או דילמא, O dilma, or do we say, כיוון דאילו חזי תרתי,
keivan de'ilu chazi tarti, if he sees this flow twice, this זיבה
Ziva flow, מצטרפא, mitztarpa, so it will combine to make him a
זב. Zav. It's the beginning of a process of a זב Zav
and he is in the category of a זב, Zav, two times
he'll be a זב. Zav. מטמיא, Matmiya, it makes him טמא. tamei.
A very good question. How far do we take the comparison to
שכבת זרע? shichvat zera? Is it just an analogy, but he's really
טמא tamei as a זב Zav and therefore it would be טמא,
tamei, or do we say it's more than an analogy, we treat
it as if, if it was only once, as if it was
שכבת זרע shichvat zera and then it's not relevant for him. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, said רבא, Rava, תא שמע, ta shema, come and
hear. זאת תורת הזב, בין גדול בין קטן. zos toras hazav bein
gadol bein katan, We have a דרשה. drasha. It says this is
the law of the זב, Zav, whether an adult or a minor.
Now, מה גדול ראייה ראשונה שלו מטמא אף קטן ראייה ראשונה נמי
מטמא. ma gadol re'iyah rishona shelo metamai af katan re'iyah rishona nami
metamai. Now you could have said it's talking about two appearances, but
no, the דרשה drasha apparently seems to be, this seems to be
the end of the ברייתא, braita, that the same way if an
adult, the first time he sees causes, it makes him טמא, tamei,
the same is true even for a minor. So fine, it was
a very nice theoretical question, right? Conceptually, what category do you put
it in after one? Is it שכבת זרע shichvat zera or is
it in the זב Zav category? But he says we have a
דרשה drasha and the דרשה drasha tells us that a minor is
just like an adult and even for the first time that he
sees. Okay, so that ended that question. Now we're not done cause
in a few minutes we'll have another similar question about how much
do we consider the first time he sees to be in the
זרע zera category, שכבת זרע shichvat zera category, or in the זב
Zav category. But for the הלכה halacha of minor at least we
put it into the זב Zav category and it does make him
טמא. tamei. בעי רב יוסף. Bei Rav Yosef. Now רב יוסף Rav
Yosef had the following question.
ראייה ראשונה של מצורע מהו שתטמא במשא. Re'iyah rishona shel metzora mahu
she'titma be'masa. The first time a מצורע metzora has a
sees his זיבה Ziva flow, does it make, is it טמא tamei
במשא? be'masa? Now what is this question about? מקום זיבה מעין הוא
ומטמיא או דילמא לאו מעין הוא. Makom ziva ma'ayan hu u'matmiya o
dilma lav ma'ayan hu. Is the source of the זיבה Ziva flow
a wellspring and it causes טומאה tumah or perhaps not a wellspring
and it doesn't? What does this mean? It means it's exactly analogous
to the question we asked about the woman's uterine flow. Normally the
woman's uterine flow you don't have to ask is it considered in
this category of fluids because it's טמא tamei just because it's blood
and it makes her a נדה niddah or זבה, zavah, except for
the special case after childbirth. So here we have something somewhat analogous
by a man. How about his זיבה Ziva flow? Now normally a
זיבה Ziva flow of a man you don't have to ask is
it a fluid or not a fluid. It's טמא tamei because it
makes him into a בעל קרי, baal keri, makes him into a
זב, Zav, right? So it's a source of טומאה, tumah, end of
question. But there's one case in which it's relatively moot. Which case
is it relatively moot? If he's already a מצורע, metzora, he's already
right has צרעת. tzaraat. So therefore if he now has a זיבה
Ziva flow, this is not going to make him טמא. tamei. He's
already טמא. tamei. It's
a little ironic because it'll make him more טמא, tamei, somebody who's
also a זב Zav or whatever is more טמא, tamei, but he's
not yet a זב. Zav. It only has the status of a
בעל קרי. baal keri. So it's a flow, it doesn't make him
any more טמא tamei than he already is. What is the status
of this flow? Is it now that it is not in this
one case a source of טומאה, tumah, is it considered like one
of the fluids of a מצורע metzora to be considered an אב
הטומאה? av hatumah? So it's very analogous to the question that we
asked about what do you call it, about the uterine flow for
a woman. Here's a case where it is in the woman's case
you could have a case where it's totally טהור. tahor. Here it's
not totally טהור, tahor, but it's relatively moot. It's moot because he's
already a מצורע. metzora. Let's read that again. ראייה ראשונה של מצורע
מהו שתטמא במשא. Re'iyah rishona shel metzora mahu she'titma be'masa. The first
time he sees, does it, is the actual, now we're asking here
not just about him, he's already טמא tamei so who cares, we're
asking about the fluid. Is the fluid itself, is it like the
fluids of a מצורע metzora and therefore even if you carry it,
not just if you touch it, it's טמא? tamei? Or is it
not like the fluids of a מצורע metzora and it is not
טמא tamei if you carry it? מקום זיבה מעין הוא ומטמיא או
דילמא לאו מעין הוא. Makom ziva ma'ayan hu u'matmiya o dilma lav
ma'ayan hu. Is the place of this flow, not the semen flow,
the other flow, is it like one of these wellsprings and it's
טמא, tamei, or perhaps not? And again it's only possible to ask
this question when it's not already making him טמא. tamei. Okay so
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא תא שמע, Amar Rava ta shema,
come and hear, זובו טמא הוא. zovo tamei hu. His flow it
is טמא. tamei. This is the פסוק pasuk by a זב. Zav.
לימד על הזב שהוא טמא. Limed al haZav shehu tamei. So it
teaches you that the flow itself is a source of טומאה. tumah.
במאי? Be'mai? Now what are we talking about? Which type of a
person's flow do we have to say it's טמא? tamei? איבעית אימא
בזב גרידא, Iba'it eima be'Zav greida, if it's only about the זב
Zav himself, דף ל"ה עמוד א', daf lamed-hei amud aleph, meaning a
simple זב Zav that his flow makes him טמא tamei and it's
the second time that he flows that makes him his second. So
when he has a full status of a זב, zav, so לאחרים
גורם טומאה לעצמו לא כל שכן? le’acherim goreim tumah l’atzmo lo kol
shekein? This is what I've been telling you all along. When the
blood when a woman has menstrual uterine blood you don't have to
make say that the blood is טמא tamei as her fluid. It's
the source of טומאה, tumah, makes her a נידה, niddah, it makes
her a זבה, zavah, so of course it itself is טמא. tamei.
Similarly if a זב zav has a flow or you know the
Torah actually is explicit that שכבת זרע shichvas zera semen is טמא,
tamei, but if a זב zav has a flow so that flow
makes him טמא tamei so of course you don't have to discuss
is it a fluid or not. It is the source of טומאה.
tumah. So that's what he is saying. Look, the פסוק pasuk that
tells me the זיבה ziva flow if it's itself טמא, tamei, I
don't need it if it's making him a זב, zav, if it's
the second flow making him a זב, zav, because of course if
it makes him a זב zav of course it itself is a
source of טומאה. tumah. אלא פשיטא, ela peshita, so what would be
the case the פסוק pasuk would have to tell me it that
it's not already obvious because it's not already making him טמא? tamei?
בזב מצורע, be-zav metzora, it's talking about a מצורע metzora who's a
זב zav where the flow is not really making him טמא tamei
because he's already טמא tamei as a מצורע. metzora. Now that's a
little funny because he might already be טמא tamei as a מצורע
metzora but this is giving him another status. But the גמרא gemara
considers that at least I might have thought that in that case
maybe the flow is not you know changing his status in a
significant way so maybe therefore it's also not טמא. tamei. Now we
understand that this פסוק pasuk based on where it appears in the
פסוק pasuk and I'm not going to go into why is talking
about the second flow. So here's the point, ואיצטריך קרא לריבויי ראייה
שנייה, u-mitztari kra leribuy b'riyah shniyah, since it has to tell me
that the second time, the second flow of this מצורע metzora it's
טמא, tamei, שמע מינה מקום זיבה לאו מעיין הוא, shma mina makom
ziva lav mayan hu, you see that it is not considered a
fluid. What is the point? It's getting a little complicated as if
it weren't before, but here's the point, okay. As I'm saying, the
basic structure is the following. You have things like the uterine blood
of a woman, the semen of a man, the זיבה ziva of
a man, all these things are אב הטומאה. av hatumah. Now normally
they're אב הטומאה av hatumah because they create טומאה, tumah, they make
the man into a זב zav and a בעל קרי ba'al keri
and the woman into a נידה niddah or זבה. zavah. But when
they don't create טומאה tumah we want to know are they considered
in this category fluids that they're also an אב הטומאה. av hatumah.
So by the woman it was relatively easy to construct it, relatively
easy. It was after her period of childbirth, she's a מצורעת, metzora'at,
that's the case. By a man it's a little more complicated because
these things will
always make him a זב, zav, but in the case that he's
also a מצורע metzora we say okay making him זב zav is
relatively moot because he's already a מצורע metzora so that's allowing us
to ask this question. Now it does not now but it says
if it's the time that he has two flows, remember the second
flow makes him a זב, zav, then we have this דרשה, drasha,
then it's relatively obvious if it's a זב zav flow and it
really makes him a זב zav then we're going to say fine
then it is טמא tamei even if he's already מצורע. metzora. But
we want to know is the first flow which is only that
of normally making him a בעל קרי, ba'al keri, what would that
status be? And here it's saying since this פסוק pasuk is telling
me that the second flow is טמא tamei we can infer that
the first flow is not. All right, is everybody with me? All
right, so let's keep on going see where the גמרא gemara goes.
So שמע מינה מקום זיבה לאו מעיין הוא, shma mina makom ziva
lav mayan hu, that just the fact that it's the place of
זיבה ziva is not enough, it is not one of these fluids
and it's only going to be a problem when it's a second
flow and really makes him a זב, zav, but the first flow
that does not it is not going to be considered one of
these fluids.
אמר ליה
רב יהודה מדסקרתא לרבא ממאי, amlei Rav Yehuda midiskarta l’Rava mima'i, how
do you know that this verse is all talking about a... is
about... cannot be talking about a simple זב? zav? How do we
know it wasn't a simple זב zav because then we would say
it'd be obvious? Obviously if it makes him a זב zav clearly
it's טמא. tamei. Not a מצורע metzora but seeing a second time.
ממאי דילמא למימרא לך בזב גרידא, mima'i dilma l’meimra lach b’zav greidah,
it's not a fancy case of a מצורע metzora where it's moot
and so on, it's a simple זב, zav, second flow, and we
have to tell us that it's considered טמא. tamei. וקאמרת u-ka'amrat and
you said we wouldn't need a פסוק pasuk for that? לאחרים גורם
טומאה לעצמו לא כל שכן, le’acherim goreim tumah l’atzmo lo kol shekein,
if it can make him into a זב zav certainly it itself
is טמא? tamei? No, that's not so obvious. שעיר המשתלח יוכיח, seir
hamishtaleach yochiach, how about the goat that's sent over in the wilderness,
you know on Yom Kippur, שגורם טומאה לאחרים, shegoreim tumah l’acherim, it
makes the guy who sends it טמא, tamei, והוא עצמו טהור, v’hu
atzmo tahor, and the goat itself remains טהור. tahor. So it's not
so obvious. Okay,
so he says look, we have a פסוק pasuk that says the
flow of a זב zav is itself טמא. tamei. You wanted to
learn that to tell the second flow of a זב. zav. You
wanted to learn that to say we're talking about a special case
of a מצורע metzora and infer that the first time he's not
טמא. tamei. It's not that who says it's a special case? It
could be a simple case of a זב zav and you still
need a פסוק pasuk to tell me that even though it makes
him a זב zav it's not obvious that the flow itself is
טמא tamei and that's what you need the פסוק pasuk for. Okay,
so we haven't proven it. אמר אביי מאי קא מיבעיא ליה, amar
Abaye maki bayei lei, I don't get the question what he's asking,
והוא דאמר רב יוסף v’hu de’amar Rav Yosef himself is the one
that said זאת תורת הזב Zot torat haZav, בין גדול בין קטן,
bein gadol bein katan. since he says remember there's this whole question
about how do you learn out that a... even a minor can
be a זב. Zav. Is it from the word לזכר ולנקבה, Lazachar
U'laneveikah, or is it from the word of זאת תורת הזב? Zos
Toras HaZav? So he learns from the words זאת תורת הזב Zos
Toras HaZav that even a minor can be a זב. Zav. וכיון
דנפקא ליה מהתם, V'keivan Denafkah Lei Meihasam, since he learns that out
from there, יתירא ליה לזכר, Yasirei Lei Lazachar, he has the word
לזכר Lazachar as extra, לרבות מצורע למעיינותיו, L'rabos Metzora L'mayanotav, ונקבה לרבות
מצורעת למעיינותיה. U'neveikah L'rabos Metzora'as L'mayanoteha. So basically he says we know,
this goes back to what we said earlier, that just like in
the debate of בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי, Beis Shammai,
that רב יוסף Rav Yosef who posed this question about the first
flow of a מצורע, Metzora, he himself says that the word לזכר
Lazachar is coming to include the the liquids of a מצורע, Metzora,
and ולנקבה U'laneveikah is coming to include the liquids of a מצורעת.
Metzora'as. So remember, this it's easy just to try to, you know,
try to focus on the basic question which is I think easy
to understand. You have the thing, the normal fluids of a female
that make her טמאה, Tmeiah, her blood. The normal fluids of a
male that make him טמא. Tamei. When you have a scenario where
they're not making them טמא, Tamei, do they have the status of
these fluids of a זכר Zachar and a נקבה? Neveikah? Of a
fluid of like a מצורע Metzora and a זב Zav and a
זבה? Zavah? So how do we learn by the female according to
בית הלל, Beis Hillel, yes? לנקבה. Laneveikah. To tell me that those
special fluids of a female, the uterine blood, that actually is also
consider is considered fluids for this הלכה. Halacha. So he says, okay,
how about the word לזכר, Lazachar, the male? So that's also we
learn the fluids of a מצורע. Metzora. So what's that coming to
teach me? So לרבות שאף
חומרי מצורע לזב גמור. L'rabos She'af Chumrei Metzora L'zav Gamur.
So now it says that the fluids of a מצורע Metzora are
are a source of טומאה. Tumah. And it links the
מצורע, Metzora, the end of the פסוק Pasuk says, you know, it
says לזוב את זובו לזכר
ולנקבה. Lazov Es Zovo Lazachar U'laneveikah. So it links the fluids of
a מצורע, Metzora, לזכר ולנקבה Lazachar U'laneveikah are the fluids of a
מצורע, Metzora, to לזוב את זובו, Lazov Es Zovo, a full זב.
Zav. So לזב גמור. L'zav Gamur. מה זב גמור מטמא במשא אף
ראייה ראשונה של מצורע מטמא
במשא. Mah Zav Gamur Metamei B'massa Af Reiyah Rishonah Shel Metzora Metamei
B'massa. So the same way the flow of a זב גמור, Zav
Gamur, the real flow of a זב Zav causes טומאה Tumah by
carrying it, so the same is true by the flow of a
מצורע. Metzora. All right, I think that was way complicated.
But
let's, yes? So anything that comes out of your body, right, is
a source of
טומאה? Tumah?
No, no, not at all. By whom? By somebody who's already טמא,
Tamei, like a זב Zav and a זבה Zavah and נדה? Niddah?
A normal person, things that come out of your body they're totally
טהור. Tahor.
But they didn't connect זב Zav to
semen in any way, right?
Well, yes, semen is טמא, Tamei, is a source of טומאה. Tumah.
Semen is a source of טומאה? Tumah? Yes.
And uterine blood is a source of טומאה, Tumah, right. זיבה, Zivah,
this this penile discharge which isn't semen is a source of טומאה.
Tumah. And if a woman is already
טמאה Tmeiah
as, not during, but but semen during the act of sex is
not?
Well, it is a טומאה, Tumah, but it doesn't, but the only
טומאה Tumah that prohibits sex is נדה Niddah and זב. Zav. All
other טומאות Tumos do not prohibit sex.
Yes, מצורע? Metzora?
Yes, but not in the same way, but yes.
And then why would anyone want to have it?
Why not? I don't understand.
It's טמא. Tamei. So?
Well, that's a טמא Tamei is not a problem unless you're a
כהן Kohen or you're going into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. People
got טמא Tamei all the time. You know,
if you were a שוחט Shochet then you were always dealing with,
I mean, you know, dead animals, although if you שחט Shecheted them
then not, but if they're נבילה, Neveilah, yes, you know and whatever.
I mean טומאה Tumah was was
the standard was טומאה. Tumah. Right? If you're not taking care and
trying to avoid all these normal things that happen in the day,
every time a woman's a נדה Niddah she's טמאה. Tmeiah. Every time
a man is a בעל קרי Baal Keri he's טמא. Tamei. Every
time there's a childbirth there's טומאה. Tumah. Every time you bury a
dead person there's טומאה. Tumah. Every time you deal with a dead
animal there's טומאה. Tumah. טומאה Tumah was was was pervasive. The whole
idea is that you have to sort of go through a process
to remove yourself from that if you want to eat תרומה Terumah
or קרבנות Korbanos or you want to go to the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. But it wasn't seen like this was somehow, you know,
like oh my god, I became טמא. Tamei.
So the baseline is טומאה? Tumah?
Pretty much. I mean, it's a little bit funny because it is
true that טומאה Tumah is used metaphorically also, not even metaphorically for
a whole idea of sin and how do you deal with that,
but I think it's important to distinguish the reality. Well, that's not,
that's not טומאה, Tumah, that's about קדושה. Kedusha. But anyway, but it
does raise interesting questions. But certainly the baseline of living a normal
life was טומאה. Tumah. Okay, yes?
You say as if an abnormality occurs within a normal way of
life, at that point you become טמא? Tamei?
Yeah, but I don't know if I'd call it an abnormality. You
know anyway. All right, I can't get into this philosophical discussion now.
We're not supposed to not have sex.
Exactly. Now. All right, moving on. Now let me just, let me
just try, I know that was a little complicated, I'll just say
one more sentence to try to summarize that and then we'll move
on. And I think one point that I forgot to mention which
is the following which maybe explains a little.
קרי, Keri, semen, and which is the first also emission of a
זב Zav has the status of semen. Normally is טמא tamei only
by touching not by carrying. Only the second flow of a זב
zav is טמא tamei by carrying. Okay so that I think was
a nuance that I, that was implicit that I forgot to mention.
So here’s the quest- what the question was. The question was look:
Normal semen is only טמא tamei or the first flow of a
זב zav by touching not by carrying. What happens though if it
is this same type of thing that comes from somebody who’s a
מצורע? metzora? And by a מצורע metzora we say that his fluids
are טמא tamei by carrying. Does this flow which is in itself
not טמא tamei by carrying, it’s like semen, but does- is it
טמא tamei as the fluids of a מצורע metzora to be- to
be טמא tamei from- by virtue you know and therefore it will
be טמא tamei as carrying? That was the question and that way
it was analogous to the question of the uterine flow of a
woman. And the answer again was a little complicated because about how
do you learn it out and so on but the basic says
look we know the second flow is. Because the second flow is
itself anyway the flow of a זב zav and the flow of
a זב, zav, the second flow, is itself by- by its own
identity it’s טמא tamei by carrying. But the question is the first
flow, which would not be טמא tamei by carrying, is it טמא
tamei by virtue of it being- it being the fluids of a
מצורע? metzora? And in the end we say yes based on a
פסוק pasuk we link the flows of a מצורע metzora to the
second flow of a זב zav and the same way the second
flow of a זב zav is טמא tamei even by carrying, the
first flow of a מצורע metzora is טמא tamei as well. But
let’s move on. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Now we get back to a somewhat easier question. אמר רב הונא
ראיה ראשונה של זב מטמא באונס. Amar Rav Huna reiyah rishonah shel
zav metamei be'ones. The first flow of a זב, zav, okay remember
the first flow of a זב zav we said was number one
it was like שכבת זרע shichvat zera in terms of the טומאה
tumah but it- it still applied to a minor. Then we also
said that it was considered like the fluids of a מצורע. metzora.
Okay now he is saying that that first appearance of a זב
zav it- it causes טומאה tumah even if it is through some
outside force. Okay the normal הלכה halacha is is that a man
has this זיבה zivah flow you first go through a series of
tests to see whether or not it was caused by something external.
Whether it’s something he ate, was it something you know was it
what type of questions do you ask. Hold on רש״י Rashi quotes
it.
Right, was it something he ate was it something he drank did
he exercise did he carry heavy things meaning so you try to
understand maybe it was brought about by something external and if so
he doesn’t become a זב. zav. So but the question is but
if somebody has a seminal emission due- during- due to something external
he is a בעל קרי. baal keri. So the question here is
again how do we look at the first flow of a זב.
zav. Is it like seminal emission and therefore it’s טמא tamei even
if it’s due to external stimulation or is it like a- or
is it like a זב zav and is not טמא tamei due
to external stimulation? So that’s the question.
Would you ask these questions by the first flow of a זב?
zav? ראיה ראשונה של זב reiyah rishonah shel zav so it says
like this: ראיה ראשונה של זב מטמא באונס reiyah rishonah shel zav
metamei be'ones does it cause טומאה באונס? tumah be'ones? שנאמר Shene'emar as
the פסוק pasuk says זאת תורת הזב ואשר תצא ממנו שכבת זרע,
Zot torat hazav va'asher tetzei mimenu shichvat zera, this is law of
the זב zav meaning one flow and the person has a seminal
emission, so שכבת זרע shichvat zera מה שכבת זרע מטמא באונס אף
ראיה ראשונה של זב מטמא באונס. ma shichvat zera metamei be'ones af
reiyah rishonah shel zav metamei be'ones. The same way seminal emission is
even based on ex- when it’s external stimulation the same is true
by the first flow of a זב. zav. So do we put
it in the שכבת זרע shichvat zera category? Or do we say
אף זוב מטמא באונס? af zov metamei be'ones? Oh it doesn’t say
the other side. But the other side is or do we give
it the normal law of a זב zav where it’s not due
to external stim- where it would not apply by external stimulation. So
תא שמע ta shema come and hear. Here we have a משנה.
Mishnah. ראה ראיה ראשונה בודקין אותו. Raah reiyah rishonah bodkin oto. If
the- the person had his first flow of a- of a זיבה
zivah flow you check him meaning to see whether it was based
on external stimulation. Did you eat something strange drink something strange and
do exercise? So you check for the first flow. So you see
that if the first flow was externally stimulated it’s not a problem.
מאי לאו לטומאה Mai lav letumah doesn’t it mean that if it
was externally stimulated it’s a question of whether it’s טמא? tamei? Says
לא לקרבן. Lo lekorban. No maybe the flow is טמא tamei regardless
but it’s saying that if it was externally stimulated it can’t combine
with flows two and three. When you have two and three flows
then you become a full טומאה tumah three flows you bring a
קרבן. korban. So for it to combine it maybe needs to be
not externally stimulated but for it to be טמא tamei even באונס
be'ones it would be טמא. tamei. That’s what it suggests. תא שמע
Ta shema okay let’s hear the משנה Mishnah continues: בשניה בודקין אותו.
Bishniyah bodkin oto. By the second flow you check. So why are
you checking by the second flow to see if- if it was
externally stimulated? למה Lemah for what purpose? אילימא לקרבן Ileima lekorban if
it’s to see whether that if it’s external you know whether you’ll
bring a קרבן korban if you have three flows אבל לטומאה לא
aval letumah lo but טומאה tumah it doesn’t matter whether it’s externally
stimulated or not? איכא? Ika? No because the פסוק pasuk says מבשרו
ולא מחמת אונסו mibesaro velo machmat onso
that it’s only when the flow is from his flesh meaning internally
it’s not something externally stimulated. אלא לאו לטומאה, ella lav letuma, it's
for טומאה. tuma. So here's basically the point: it says when the
זב zav has the second flow, you check that flow that there
was not an אונס, onos, so it's not external stimulation. So the
גמרא Gemara says ואידך ואידך veidach veidach we know the הלכה halacha
is that if the second flow is externally stimulated, it's אונס, onos,
it's not טמא. tamei. So when it says you check the second
flow, you're checking to determine is it טמא tamei or
not. So it also says, and it also says you check the
first flow. So presumably, if the second flow the check is to
determine if it's טמא, tamei, the first flow is also to determine
it's טמא. tamei. ומדסיפא לטומאה, umideiseifa letuma, since the second flow it's
to determine if it's טמא, tamei, which it would not be if
it's אונס, onos, רישא נמי לטומאה, reisha nami letuma, so the first
checking the first flow is also to determine it's טמא. tamei. So
again you see if it's אונס, onos, the first flow is not
טמא. tamei. So he says מידי איריא midi irya what, that's a
proof? הכי קאמר hachi ka’amar each one in its own category. The
second flow is not טמא tamei if it's אונס. onos. The first
flow maybe is טמא tamei regardless because it's like שכבת זרע, shichvat
zera, but if it's externally stimulated, it doesn't combine with two and
three to bring a קרבן. korban. All right. So now it says,
ומידי סו- הכי קאמר. umidi so- hachi ka’amar. תא שמע ta shema
we'll try again. רבי אלעזר אומר Rabbi Elazar omer אף בשלישי בודקין
אותו, af bashlishi bodkin oto, you even check the third flow to
determine if it was an אונס onos and if it's an אונס
onos you don't bring a קרבן. korban. By the second flow a
זב zav has a seven day טומאה, tuma, by the third flow
he brings a קרבן. korban. So מפני הקרבן mipnei hakorban you have
to check the third flow that it's
not אונס onos in order to determine a קרבן. korban. מכלל michlal
from this you can infer דתנא קמא מפני הטומאה קאמר, detana kama
mipnei hatuma ka'amar, but the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is saying that
you never check for קרבן korban purposes, you're only checking for טומאה
tuma purposes. And if you're only checking for טומאה tuma purposes, even
when you checked flow number one, it was for טומאה tuma purposes.
So לא, lo, גמרא Gemara says no. לכולי עלמא לקרבן, lecholay alma
lekorban, everybody can agree that sometimes you check for a קרבן. korban.
והכא באתים קמיפלגי, vehacha be’etim kamifligi,
they debate when how you interpret the word את et in a
פסוק passuk whether it's coming to teach you something. רבנן לא דרשי
אתים rabanan lo darshi etim ורבי אלעזר דרשי אתים. veRabbi Elazar darshi
etim.
The רבנן Rabbanan learn it out and רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar does
not. What does this mean? רבנן לא דרשי אתים. rabanan lo darshi
etim. Here's the פסוק. passuk. הזב חדא, hazav chada, זובו תרתי. zovo
tarti.
Here's the פסוק passuk says והזב את זובו לזכר ולנקבה, veha-zav et
zovo lazachar velanekeva,
the one who has the flow for the male and the female.
So הזב hazav one flow. זובו תרתי zovo tarti two flows. לזכר
בשלישי הקישה רחמנא לנקבה. lazachar bashlishi hiksha rachmana lanekeva. So
it says לזכר ולנקבה. lazachar velanekeva. So a woman who's a זבה
zava always brings a קרבן. korban. So by the time you get
to לזכר ולנקבה lazachar velanekeva we're talking about bringing a קרבן. korban.
Okay? So הזב את זובו hazav et zovo two flows. Then לזכר
ולנקבה lazachar velanekeva by the third flow he's like a woman, and
like a woman also, a woman's blood makes her טמאה tmeiah even
באונס, be’onos, okay even if it is an אונס. onos. So basically
what the Rabbis say is this הלכה halacha that the man's flow
is only when it's not באונס be'onos is only the first two,
הזב את זובו. hazav et zovo. But by the time you get
to the third flow לזכר, lazachar, you're already like the לנקבה lanekeva
and the third flow does even באונס be’onos is significant. That's what
the Rabbis say. ורבי אלעזר דריש אתים veRabbi Elazar darish etim
now he he says the את et means something. הזב חדא, hazav
chada, את תרתי, et tarti, זובו תלת. zovo tlat. ברביעי הקישה רחמנא
לנקבה. berevi’i hiksha rachmana lanekeva.
The only time that it doesn't matter if it's externally stimulated is
by the fourth flow. But even to bring even for the third
flow it has to not be an אונס. onos. So what is
the גמרא Gemara saying?
What is the debate whether you check the third flow for אונס
onos or not? It is not a debate whether any of the
flows doesn't matter for קרבן korban whether it's אונס. onos. First and
second flow you will only lead to a קרבן korban if it
is not באונס. be’onos. The only question is, or it's not a
קרבן korban issue, it's a question of flows one and two versus
flows three. To bring a קרבן korban to become טמא tamei you
need it not to be באונס, be’onos, that's true about one and
two. But by three, which is about the קרבן, korban, so there
the Rabbis say by three already אונס onos doesn't matter, don't bother
checking, you'll bring a קרבן korban even if three is באונס. be’onos.
ורבי אלעזר veRabbi Elazar says no, even by three it can't be
באונס. be’onos. When does it when does it not matter if it's
אונס? onos? By four. Now who cares about four? You're already טמא
tamei you're already bringing a קרבן. korban. So four is you're trying
to count your seven clean days and then you get a flow.
That flow, even if it's באונס, be’onos, everybody agrees doesn't matter. So
anyway, the debate of רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar and the רבנן Rabbanan
is does the third flow which leads to a קרבן, korban, can
that be באונס be’onos or not? But the first two, everybody would
agree cannot be באונס, be’onos, and the first one, maybe it's טמא
tamei regardless. But in order to lead to a קרבן, korban, then
it cannot be באונס. be’onos. So we have not yet proven the
story of the first flow whether אונס onos matters or not. So
תא שמע, ta shema, the גמרא Gemara is going to try again,
come in here. רבי יצחק אומר Rabbi Yitzchak omer ולא זב בכלל
בעל קרי היה. velo zav bichlal ba'al keri haya. One minute. A
זב zav was in the category of a בעל קרי. ba'al keri.
And what does that mean? Presumably the first flow of a זב
zav you're like a בעל קרי. ba'al keri. ולמה יצא velama yatza
why was a זב zav singled out as a special category? להקל
עליו ולהחמיר עליו lehakel alav ulehachmir alav in ways it's more lenient
and in ways it's more strict. להקל עליו lehakel alav it's more
lenient שאין מטמא באונס she'ein metamei be'onos like we said a בעל
קרי ba'al keri is טמא tamei even by אונס. onos. A
זב... zav...
It's only when it's not אונס, ones, not externally stimulated. ולהחמיר עליו,
ulehachmir alav, it's more strict, שהוא עושה אבי, she'hu oseh avi, a
זב zav is much more strict
than a בעל קרי. ba'al keri. First of all it's seven days,
which this doesn't even mention, but שהוא עושה משכב ומושב, she'hu oseh
mishkav umoshav, that the seats you sit on an אב הטומאה, av
hatumah, זב zav is much much more strict than a בעל קרי.
ba'al keri. Now אימא, eima, which stage are we talking about? אילימא
בראייה שנייה, ilema biriyah sheniyah, the second time he sees, היכי הוה
בכלל קרי? heichi hava biklal keri? What do you mean a זב
zav was like a בעל קרי? ba'al keri? If a זב zav
saw twice, he was never like a
בעל קרי. ba'al keri. אלא בראייה ראשונה, ella biriyah rishonah, we mean
after the first time you saw, that you have the same laws
as a בעל קרי ba'al keri if a person has a flow.
וקתני vekatani להקל עליו שאינו מטמא באונס. lehakel alav she'eino metame be'ones.
And it says, look, he is in a category of a זב,
zav, he's not causing טומאה באונס. tumah be'ones. So it says, since
it says a זב zav is like a בעל קרי, ba'al keri,
we're talking after one flow. That's when a זב zav is like
a בעל קרי. ba'al keri. And it says, but he's more lenient
than a בעל קרי ba'al keri because it doesn't apply when it's
באונס. be'ones. So you see that the first flow, if it's באונס,
be'ones, does not make him
טמא. tameh. גמרא Gemara says ותסברא? vetisbora? Does that make sense that
that's how you want to read it?
להחמיר עליו שהוא עושה משכב ומושב, lehachmir alav shehu oseh mishkav umoshav,
it says he's more strict because he makes the seats he sits
on into an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. בראייה ראשונה בר משכב ומושב
הוא? biriyah rishonah bar mishkav umoshav hu? Does that apply after seeing
one? Right, we can't read the ברייתא braisa talking when he's in
his state of having seen one, because then how does it make
sense to say that he makes the seats into an אב הטומאה?
av hatumah? That doesn't apply after one, that's only somebody who is
a זב. zav. אלא הכי קאמר, ella hachi ka'amar, here's how this
whole thing has to be read. And this is clearly the פשט
pshat of this ברייתא. braisa. רבי יצחק אומר בלאו זב בכלל קרי
היה בראייה ראשונה. Rabbi Yitzchak omer belo zav biklal keri haya biriyah
rishonah. When he saw his first flow, he had the status of
a בעל קרי. ba'al keri. למה יצא ראייה שנייה? lama yatza biriyah
sheniyah? How does the second flow make him different? So by the
second flow, then להקל עליו ולהחמיר עליו. lehakel alav ulehachmir alav.
There's ways he's more lenient, there's ways he's more strict. להקל עליו
שאינו מטמא באונס. lehakel alav she'eino metame be'ones. It's more lenient that
at the second flow it does not a problem if it's an
אונס. ones. ולהחמיר עליו שהוא עושה משכב ומושב. ulehachmir alav shehu oseh
mishkav umoshav. But the second flow is clearly much more strict because
the טומאה tumah is seven days and it's a טומאה tumah that
makes the seats טמא tameh as well. So it sounds, the גמרא
Gemara doesn't spell it out and it's not explicit, but that makes
it sound very much that the first flow is מטמא באונס. metame
be'ones. So the גמרא Gemara does not really, well the גמרא Gemara
does not really spell that out, but all right, but the interesting
thing is that although it was clear to the גמרא Gemara that
a minor can have a status of a זב zav after one
flow, and we don't put it into the בעל קרי ba'al keri
category for that, but when it comes to the issue of אונס
ones versus non, the גמרא Gemara does not think it's all the
same הלכה. halacha. It could be in some ways it's not like
a בעל קרי ba'al keri because it applies even to minors and
in other ways maybe it is, maybe it even causes טומאה tumah
even באונס, be'ones, and
that's specifically אונס ones though, wouldn't you say? No.
Anyway, and that, and that, and the גמרא Gemara doesn't come to
a clear conclusion, but the way it read this ברייתא braisa certainly
seems to indicate that that would be true even באונס, be'ones, that
the status only changes by the second. So it's actually quite clear
that it's a split vote about in some ways it is like
a בעל קרי, ba'al keri, in some ways not. Now the גמרא
Gemara ends this by a nice statement about the differences of the
flow. As I said by a woman, the difference is what time
during the month. Here the גמרא Gemara describes the physical differences. אמר
רב הונא, amar Rav Huna, זוב, zov, the flow that is the
זוב zov flow, not the שכבת זרע, shichvas zera, דומה למי בצקי
של שעורין. domeh lemei batzei shel se'orin. It's like the water of
barley dough. I have no idea what the water of barley dough
looks like. Okay. זוב בא מבשר המת. zov ba mibasar hamess. Now
the flow of the זוב, zov, not the שכבת זרע, shichvas zera,
comes from the non-erect penis. שכבת זרע בא מבשר החי. shichvas zera
ba mibasar hachai. שכבת זרע shichvas zera comes from an erect penis.
זוב דיהה. zov diha. זוב zov is like pale. ודומה ללובן ביצה
המוזרת. vedomeh leloven beitzah hamuzeres. It's like the white of a non-fertilized
egg. שכבת זרע קשורה. shichvas zera kshura. שכבת זרע, shichvas zera, semen,
is more viscous, it's more like it holds itself together. ודומה ללובן
ביצה שאינה מוזרת. vedomeh leloven beitzah she'eina muzeres. And it looks like
the white of a fertilized egg. I'm not sure that I have
no idea, I'm not a farmer, whether a fertilized egg looks the
same or not. רש"י Rashi says that's what מוזרת muzeres means. I
thought the word מוזרת muzeres meant more like it was beaten or
scrambled or not. But anyway. So that is the physical difference, זוב
zov versus
זרע. zera.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara goes, that is that. So what we
have was interesting cross categories is basically the thing here. On the
one hand the first flow of a זב, zav, totally discussion about
to what degree is it like שכבת זרע, shichvas zera, not like
שכבת זרע shichvas zera for the basic question of does it apply
to a minor on the one hand, is it מטמא באונס? metame
be'ones? And then the other question which was basically the משנה, Mishnah,
or the flows that normally cause טומאה, tumah, whether it's the uterine
flow of a woman, or whether it is the זיבה ziva flow,
the first זיבה ziva flow of a man which the גמרא Gemara
tries to make analogous. What is their status when they're not causing
טומאה? tumah? Are they like the fluids of a זב zav and
a זבה? zavah? זבה. Zavah. And that in the end by the
uterine flow of a woman was a debate of בית הלל, Beis
Hillel, בית שמאי. Beis Shamai. Now we get to the third category:
דם היולדת שלא טבלה. Dam Hayoledes Shelo Tavlah. This is somewhat similar;
this actually גמרא Gemara should go pretty quickly. This is a woman
that gave childbirth, did not go to the מקוה, Mikva,
and now she, it's one week or two weeks later and she's
in this period of טהרה, Tahara, and now she has a flow.
What's the story with that flow? So that seems to be very
analogous, right? Because the blood itself seems to be, should be טהור
Tahor because it's in the 33 or the 66 days, but she
herself is טמאה, Tmeiah, she hasn't gone to the מקוה. Mikva. What's
the status, what's the status here? Right, you understand the same point?
It's the period of טהרה, Tahara, she's still a יולדת, Yoledes, she
hasn't gone to the מקוה. Mikva. Is it like her fluids or
not? But the interesting thing here is that both בית הלל Beis
Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shamai are stricter. בית שמאי Beis Shamai
here agrees that it is like her fluids, and בית הלל Beis
Hillel says it's not just like her fluids, it's really like דם
נדה, Dam Niddah, and the difference being that even if it's dry,
it still causes טומאה. Tumah. So everybody says this is one degree
stricter than what we were talking about before. So let's see why.
תני, Tani, we taught in a ברייתא. Braisa. אמרו להן בית הלל
לבית שמאי, Amru Lahen Beis Hillel L'Beis Shamai, בית הלל Beis Hillel
said to בית שמאי, Beis Shamai, אי אתם מודים בנדה שלא טבלה
וראתה דם שטמאה? Iy Atem Modim B'Niddah Shelo Tavlah V'Ra'asah Dam Shete'meiah?
I don't get it. Don't you agree that if a woman is
a נדה, Niddah, even after her seven days are up, if she
hasn't gone to the מקוה Mikva and she bleeds, that that blood
is real דם נדה Dam Niddah or דם זיבה Dam Ziva and
it's fully טמא Tamei even if it dries up? So, עכשיו, Achshav,
so why here is it any different? This woman hasn't gone to
the
מקוה. Mikva. Where were תאמרו, Tomru, so אמרו להם בית שמאי, Amru
Lahem Beis Shamai, בית שמאי Beis Shamai said back, לא, Lo, no.
What type of comparison is that? אם אמרתם בנדה שאפילו טבלה וראתה
טמאה, Im Amartem B'Niddah She'afilu Tavlah V'Ra'asah Te'meiah, by נדה, Niddah, okay,
she's gone to the מקוה Mikva but the next time she bleeds
that makes her טמאה, Te'meiah, so of course the blood is a
source of טומאה. Tumah. תאמרו ביולדת שאם טבלה וראתה שהיא טהורה? Tomru
B'Yoledes She'im Tavlah V'Ra'asah Shehi Tehorah? By the יולדת, Yoledes, had she
gone to the מקוה, Mikva, this blood would do nothing to her.
So therefore, this is a period where the blood is טהור Tahor
and therefore, I am not going to treat this as a source
of a טומאה, Tumah, even though she has not gone to the
מקוה, Mikva, the blood is still טהור; Tahor; it's during the 33
or the 66 days. So
אמרו להם, Amru Lahem, so בית הלל Beis Hillel said back to
בית שמאי, Beis Shamai, יולדת בזובה תוכיח. Yoledes B'Zovah Tochiach. How about
a woman who gives birth when she's a זבה? Zavah? שאם טבלה
וראתה לאחר ימי ספירה טהורה. She'im Tavlah V'Ra'asah L'achar Yemei Sfirah Tehorah.
If she were to go to the מקוה Mikva after her seven
days, then she's
טהורה, Tehorah, and then she bled during the 33 or 66 days,
she's טהורה. Tehorah. לא טבלה וראתה, Lo Tavlah V'Ra'asah, if she hasn't
gone to the מקוה Mikva and she bleeds during her, when she's
trying to get her seven clean days as being a זבה, Zavah,
טמאה, Te'meiah, she's טמאה. Te'meiah. Now, okay, it isn't as easy as
I thought. So I don't know why I thought, but anyway, so
here is the point. The point is like this. Okay, again, the
case they're debating is that it's after her week or two weeks,
she hasn't gone to the מקוה, Mikva, she's טמאה, Tmeiah, but the
blood should be טהור. Tahor. And nevertheless, בית הלל Beis Hillel are
saying I'm treating the blood as fully טמא. Tamei. Okay? Maybe it's
easy to jump ahead and tell you what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say the reasoning of בית הלל Beis Hillel is. בית
הלל's Beis Hillel reasoning is that when does the תורה Torah change,
give her this 33 or 66 days of טהרה? Tahara? When does
it change the status of the blood? Not just when she enters
into day 15 or day 8, but it's after she goes to
the מקוה Mikva and she's in this period. That בית הלל Beis
Hillel actually understands that her status of דם טהור Dam Tahor doesn't
begin until after the מקוה. Mikva. Okay, גמרא Gemara is going to
say it later; you'll trust me for now. So that's what בית
הלל's Beis Hillel position is about. Okay, so now, how does this
relate to the debate, so בית שמאי Beis Shamai says no, no,
no, it's still טהור Tahor blood. Maybe I'll, you know, treat it
like her fluids or something like that, even though normally I don't.
Maybe here I'll agree to you, I didn't agree by the מצורע,
Metzora, but maybe I'll agree here, whatever, רבנן, Rabbanan, but nevertheless, it's
not fundamentally טמא Tamei blood. Okay, it's just when it gets into
the day 8 or day 15, it becomes טהור. Tahor. That's how
the גמרא Gemara is going to explain the debate. Now, what is
trying to bring the proof from the זבה? Zavah? The proof from
the זבה Zavah is the following. They both agree that while that's
true, that when you get into day 8 or day 15 according
to בית שמאי, Beis Shamai, the blood is טהור Tahor even if
you haven't gone to the מקוה. Mikva. If the woman still needs
seven clean days as a זבה, Zavah, she became, she gave birth
while she was a זבה. Zavah. זבה Zavah needs seven clean days
before she can be טהורה. Tehorah. There they agree that bleeding that
occurs during the 33 or 66 days while she's a זבה Zavah
is still considered זבה Zavah blood. Okay? The bleeding during 33 and
66 can't be new טומאה, Tumah, but if she's already a זבה,
Zavah, that bleeding is זבה Zavah blood, and therefore it prevents her
from getting her seven clean days. That they agree on. So now
you understand that בית הלל's Beis Hillel argument to בית שמאי Beis
Shamai is there's a good analogy. Look, if she's טמאה Te'meiah as
a זבה Zavah and you agree that the bleeding during the 33
or 66 days is still considered, you know, דם Dam that makes
her טמאה, Te'meiah, so if she's טמאה Tmeiah the יולדת, Yoledes, it
should be the same thing. If she hasn't gone to the מקוה
Mikva and she's still טמאה, Te'meiah, the blood should still be considered
טמא. Tamei. I'm going to be let us זו תוכיח. zov tochiach.
So yeah, two lines before it gets wide. שאם טבלה וראתה לאחר
ימי ספירת טהרה, She-im tavla v'rasta l'achar yemei sefirat taharah, if she's
gone to the מקווה mikvah and then she bleeds during 33 or
66, no problem. לא טבלה וראתה, Lo tavla v'raatah, if she didn't
go to the מקווה mikvah and she's bled during the during 33
and 66, if she's still trying to get her seven clean days,
טמאה, t'meiah, then the blood is טמא. tamei. So if it's true
by a זבה zavah trying to get her seven clean days, it
should be true by a יולדת yoledes that hasn't gone to the
מקווה. mikvah. אמרו להם, Amru lahem, they said back to them, no,
הוא הדין והוא התשובה. hu hadin v'hu hatshuva. You know what? The
same thing we said by יולדת yoledes we'll say here, we're not
impressed. Okay. Yeah, fine, same thing, fine, יולדת yoledes also not a
problem, זבה zavah also not a problem during the 33 and 66
days. So once גמרא Gemara says one minute,
למימר דפליגי, L'eimar d'p'ligi, you're saying that they argue by the case
of a זבה zavah that that בית שמאי Beit Shammai would say
it's not a problem? והתנן, V'ha tnan, our משנה Mishnah says,
ומודין ביולדת בזבה U'modim b'yoledes b'zavah שמטמא לח ויבש, she'metamei lach v'yavesh,
that it is a problem. So it says okay, they don't fully
agree by a זבה, zavah, it's a חילוק. chilluk. לא קשיא כאן
שספרה כאן שלא ספרה. Lo kashya kan she'safra kan she'lo safra. It
depends whether she's had her seven clean days or not. So it's
like this: if she's in the middle of her seven clean days
and she's bleeding, then בית שמאי Beit Shammai agrees. She's still a
זבה, zavah, she's trying to get clean days, the bleeding during 33
or 66 prevents it from being a clean day and she has
to start all over again. But let's say she's got her seven
clean days and she just hasn't gone to the מקווה. mikvah. That
is much more similar to the יולדת yoledes that hasn't gone to
the מקווה. mikvah. Okay, everything is done except going to the מקווה.
mikvah.
So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says the same way I say
if she hasn't gone to the מקווה mikvah and she bleeds during
33 66 it's not a problem, I'll say if she's a זבה
zavah and she's counted her clean days and hasn't gone to the
מקווה, mikvah, any bleeding after everything else is done even if I
haven't gone to the מקווה mikvah is not a problem. If it's
during the seven clean days that already a different story. So but
that's בית שמאי Beit Shammai says. I don't care if she's gone
to the מקווה, mikvah, once she is out of her יולדת yoledes
period, out of her זבה zavah period, the blood is not a
problem. And בית הלל Beit Hillel says the blood does not change
status until she's gone to the מקווה. mikvah.
You can see it slightly differently is because not בית הלל Beit
Hillel בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, but they each are more מחמיר machmir
step up is because of this פסוק pasuk which we'll get to
later.
Not a פסוק, pasuk, it's a no, the בית שמאי Beit Shammai
we don't even know, בית שמאי Beit Shammai the only reason they're
more מחמיר machmir is a דרבנן d'rabbanan we haven't even discussed that.
בית הלל, Beit Hillel, the definition of when do you say the
blood of a יולדת, yoledes, בית הלל, Beit Hillel, when do you
say the blood of a יולדת yoledes becomes טהור tahor and they
say not during not day eight automatically, after going to the מקווה.
mikvah. והתניא, V'ha tanya, we taught a ברייתא braita just like that,
יולדת בזבה שספרה ולא טבלה וראתה, Yoledes b'zavah she'safra v'lo tavla v'raatah,
she had her seven days she just hasn't gone to the מקווה.
mikvah. הלכו בית שמאי לשיטתם ובית הלל לשיטתם, Halchu Beit Shammai l'shitatam
v'Beit Hillel l'shitatam, then the 33 and 66 days the bleeding there
after the seven days of a זבה zavah is according to בית
שמאי Beit Shammai is not an issue. So basically what it boils
down to is right, why בית שמאי's Beit Shammai more מחמיר machmir
is a דרבנן d'rabbanan issue, we're not getting into that at least
not now let's not distract ourselves. The focus here, this debate, before
the debate was, is the uterine blood like a when it's not
טמא, tamei, is that like the fluids of a זב zav and
a זבה. zavah. Here the debate is a debate about the status
of a יולדת. yoledes. When is the Torah מטהר m'taher the blood
of a יולדת? yoledes? Okay, after she's gone to the מקווה mikvah
or as soon as I mean day eight or day fifteen after
the מקווה mikvah or automatically day eight and day fifteen. It's a
simple question of when is the Torah מטהר m'taher the blood of
a יולדת yoledes and that and that is what they debate. Okay,
בית שמאי Beit Shammai would concede if she's trying to get her
שבעה נקיים, shivah neki'im, but if she's done with her שבעה נקיים
shivah neki'im as a זבה zavah then he says it happens automatically.
And now although we only have two three minutes, let us start
a introduce the debate of רב ושמואל Rav v'Shmuel which helps frame
all of these issues in a nice concise conceptual way. So איתמר,
itmar, I'm serious, I'm totally serious. So איתמר, itmar, רב אמר מעיין
אחד הוא התורה טימאתו והתורה טיהרתו. Rav amar ma'ayan echad hu hatorah
timaso v'hatorah tiharto. Why does the Torah say that blood until day
seven is טמא tamei and from day eight and on is טהור?
tahor? Or until day fourteen is טמא tamei until day fifteen and
on is טהור? tahor? So רב's Rav becoming maybe maybe the Torah
is thinking that it's a different source of blood. Maybe the blood
from days you know eight till forty are not uterine blood, maybe
they're coming from somewhere else. Or it doesn't matter if it's uterine
blood, the Torah just says even if it's uterine blood now it's
going to be טהור, tahor, it's coming after childbirth now it's טהור.
tahor. So that's the debate of רב Rav and לוי. Levi. רב
Rav said it is one wellspring. It all has the same source,
it's all uterine blood. The Torah says until day seven is טמא,
tamei, day eight and on it's טהור. tahor. Until day fourteen is
טמא, tamei, day fifteen and on it's טהור. tahor. התורה טימאתו והתורה
טיהרתו. Hatorah timaso v'hatorah tiharto. It's all the same source. It's just
a status difference that the Torah gives it. But לוי אמר, Levi
amar, לוי Levi says, שני מעיינות הן. shnei ma'ayanos hein. Nope they
are two different sources. נסתם הטמא, nistam hatamei, on day seven the
end of day seven the טמא tamei source closes, it's no longer
coming from the uterus, נפתח הטהור niftach hatahor and it's coming from
a different source. Okay, so it's a physical difference. And on day
40 or day 80 נסתם. nistam. the טהור tahor source of blood
closes, נפתחה הטמא niftacha hatamei and the טמא tamei one opens. So
לוי Levi says it's a physical difference, רב Rav says it's a
halachic difference. Now this leads to fascinating questions about how do you
determine about like what situations can be one without the other.
Which he's reading the whole way through.
Very good, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. מאי
בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What is an example of something that רב Rav
and לוי Levi would debate? איכא בינייהו שופעת מתוך שבעה לאחר שבעה.
ika beinaihu shofat mitoch shiva le'achar shiva. She's bleeding from before the
end of day seven into day eight, or מתוך ארבעה עשר לאחר
ארבעה עשר mitoch arba-asar le'achar arba-asar or by a girl before the
end of 14 into day 15. Or and that's at the beginning
of the process or the end of the process. ומתוך ארבעים לאחר
ארבעים umitoch arbaim le'achar arbaim from day 40 the end of day
40 until day 41. ומתוך שמונים לאחר שמונים umitoch shmonim le'achar shmonim
or the end of day 80 until day 81. Okay, it's a
continuous flow. If it's a continuous flow, you or you can assume
that it's not all of a sudden that one spigot turned off
and the other turned on. If it's continuous coming from the same
source. So according to רב, Rav, it's not a question of its
source. It's an arbitrary הלכה halacha that the תורה Torah just status
the תורה Torah assigns. So לרב רישא לקולא וסיפא לחומרא. le'Rav reisha
lekula vesifa lechumra. The first case when it's flowing from the טמא
tamei days into the טהור tahor days, רב Rav would be lenient.
As soon as day 8 hits or 15 hits, poof, it becomes
טהור, tahor, even if it's the same source. But at the end
from day 40 to 41 or 80 to 81, he would be
strict. As soon as day 41 hits, poof, it becomes טמא. tamei.
81, poof, it becomes טמא, tamei, even if it's the same flow.
So the first the beginning of the process would be מקל, meikel,
the end would be מחמיר. machmir. And לוי Levi would be the
reverse. וללוי רישא לחומרא וסיפא לקולא. ul'Levi reisha lechumra vesifa lekula. It's
the reverse. The beginning, if it's the same flow
from day 7 into day 8, then it's טמא. tamei. It's the
same flow and it's from the טומאה tuma source. On the other
hand, at the end of the process, day 40 into 41, if
it's the same source, then it's טהור. tahor. So לוי Levi is
very much he says it relates to a physical reality and רב
Rav says it's a pure halachic reality. And the גמרא Gemara will
continue with this tomorrow and move it, turn it back to בית
הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. Just to test you,
what does it seem clear is בית הלל's Beis Hillel's position on
this? Can you figure out, מעיין אחד או שני מעיינות? ma'ayan echad
o shnei mayanos? בית הלל Beis Hillel says it only becomes טהור
tahor after she not only after day 8, but also after she
goes to the מקוה. mikvah. So what does that sound like? Two?
No, one. If it was physical, who needs going to the מקוה?
mikvah? It's a halachic status change. So if it's halachic, you could
say not only does day 8, you also need to go to
the מקוה. mikvah. But if it's physical, who would need that? All
right, so keep that in mind. We will continue this discussion tomorrow.